<gameinfo id="light1">Press L to toggle your headlamp</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="light2">Press J to see a journal of the text you'll be reading, W, A, S, and D to move around, Space bar to jump</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="light3">If you're looking at an item and its name appears, you can press the mouse left button to gather it</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="inventory1">Press O to display your Chemical Synthesis Tool</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="inventory2">You can select an element from the array below by clicking on it, and place it in the tool by clicking on a cell. Press Z to undo an action</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="inventory3">The two first symbols are single and double covalent bonds (you can use as many as you need, no need to gather those). To position them, first click on a cell (which hopefully contains an element already) and then on an adjacent cell (no diagonals though)</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="inventory4">You can use these bonds and elements to craft the compounds you'll need to progress. When you're ready, press P to synthesize it, and if the diagram is correct, the compound will be added to your inventory. To use it, simply click on it when and where you need it</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="water1">To craft compounds, the Chemical Synthesis Tool requires Lewis diagrams made from elements you gather in your environment. You'll learn how to draw them throughout the game. The Tool has some limitations, so you can ignore diagonal bonds</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="water2">Hydrogen atoms can only bond once. This is because a single covalent bond involves one pair of electrons, and hydrogen needs 2 electrons to be full. This is an exception, as other atoms need 8 electrons. This is known as the octet rule, atoms tend to combine to satisfy it</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="methane1">Double covalent bonds involve 2 pairs of electrons. You can figure out if single or double bonds are needed with the octet rule and with the number of valence electrons the atoms have</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="methane2">Open your Periodic Table by pressing I. Each column (except the pink-colored ones) group atoms by their number of valence electrons. For example, hydrogen has 1, calcium (Ca) has 2, aluminum (Al) has 3, fluorine (F) has 7</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="methane3">When crafting a compound, each single bond you add represents 2 electrons, shared between two atoms. If an atom doesn't have 8 atoms after you sum up its lone electrons and those shared through bonds, you might have to add double bonds or to redraw the structure</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="acid1">It's often important to consider formal charges when drawing structures. You can calculate each atom's formal charge by substracting each bond (1 for a single, 2 for a double one) and each lone electron from its initial number of valence electrons</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="acid2">If the formal charge is not zero, you might be able to reconfigure the diagram (change the shape or the type of bonds). The octet rule can be violated in some cases</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisCenterTip1">To start a Lewis diagram, you could have to determine the atoms that go in the center of the structure, and this atom has to bond with many other atoms. It's a good idea to choose the least electronegative atom</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisCenterTip2">Open your Periodic Table by pressing I. Generally, it should be the atom that's farthest from Fluorine (F)</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisValenceTip1">Often, you can simply add the number of single bonds (and twice the number of double bonds) to the initial number of valence electrons to determine if the octet is full</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisValenceTip2">Here's an example: Selenium (Se) could bond with 2 atoms with a single bond, or 1 atom with a double bond, because it needs 2 more electrons to bring its 6 valence electrons to 8, as per the octet rule. Therefore, 4 electrons would be involved in bonding (as 2 come from the other atom and 2 from the selenium atom), and 4 would be lone electrons</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisFormulaTip1">It's good to keep in mind that formulas can sometimes indicates how the different atoms are connected in a compound</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisChargeTip1">Here's an example of how to calculate a formal charge: Let's assume an Oxygen atom shares one single bond with another atom and therefore has 6 lone electrons. The initial valence number was 6, minus 6 lone electrons, minus 1 electron from the single bond. Its formal charge is therefore -1, which is not ideal.</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisAcidTip1">Some elements from the third row down can expand their valence shells and hold more than 8 electrons</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisCTFETip1">CTFE's formula can also be written out as CF₂CClF</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="lewisEthanolTip1">It's good to know that another common way to write out ethanol's formula is CH₃CH₂OH</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="navigationTip1">If you're missing something to synthetize a compound, it might be good to go back and look again for a place you didn't notice</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="navigationTipQuantity1">If you don't have a large enough quantity of a given element, try to search the location where you initially found the element</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="pre1">Press O to display your Chemical Synthesis Tool</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="pre2">You can select an element (H, O, C, etc.) from the array below by clicking on it, and place it in the tool by clicking on a cell. Press Z to undo an action</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="pre3">The two first symbols are single and double covalent bonds (you can use as many as you need). To position them, first click on a cell (which hopefully contains an element already) and then on an adjacent cell (no diagonals though)</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="pre4">Draw the Lewis diagram of the compound displayed at the top of the tool (the first one should be CO2). When you're ready, press P to synthesize it. After 3 compounds, the game will start</gameinfo>
<gameinfo id="end1">End</gameinfo>
